<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Bishop of London's eighth letter to his clergy upon a conference how they ought to behave themselves under the Toleration.</title>
            <author>Compton, Henry, 1632-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5665</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12715819</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12715819</idno>
            <idno type="VID">200301</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 200301)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 959:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Bishop of London's eighth letter to his clergy upon a conference how they ought to behave themselves under the Toleration.</title>
                  <author>Compton, Henry, 1632-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benj. Motte,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Toleration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:200301:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:200301:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BISHOP OF LONDON's EIGHTH LETTER To his CLERGY, Upon a CONFERENCE <hi>How they ought to behave themſelves</hi> UNDER THE TOLERATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by BENJ. MOTTE, 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:200301:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:200301:2"/>
            <head>THE Biſhop of <hi>LONDON</hi>'S EIGHTH LETTER TO HIS CLERGY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Good</hi> BROTHER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now Three Years ſince I firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun this Conference in my Dioceſe; and therefore it can be no wonder, if many of you ſhould have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got what Diſcourſe paſſed upon this occaſion: For I begun in 1689. and concluded not till the laſt Summer 1691.</p>
            <p>But beſides this, and my conſtant Cuſtom of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating to you from time to time the ſubſtance of what had been the entertainment of our Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: I find my ſelf obliged to publiſh the Heads of this Conference, and in what manner we purſued it, that I may take off the Edge of ſome unadviſed and falſe Repreſentations that have been made, as if I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:200301:3"/>ſigned to diſturb and interrupt that Repoſe which the Laws have given to Diſſenters. Whereas, God is my Witneſs, I had no ſuch Thoughts; but as much the contrary as poſſible. Which will beſt appear by what follows.</p>
            <p n="1">I. It was enquired, What Diſcipline we had left for the ſupport of our Church, ſince the Act of <hi>Toleration.</hi> And this we did, by conſidering what Statutes were ſuſpended, upon that account: and what Conditions were to be obſerved by ſuch, as ſhould have the benefit of that Suſpenſion. For it is a very reaſonable Proverb, <hi>Even Reckonings make long Friends.</hi> Should we break in upon one anothers Boundaries, and not keep every one within his own Line; it would cauſe ſuch continual Strife and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, as would inevitably bring in <hi>Confuſion and every evil Work.</hi> But if we will be limited by thoſe Rules, which the Law has ſet, and be careful not to intrench upon one anothers Privileges: This will be the only means to create a Confidence and good Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding among us for the conſervation of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace. For ſuch Behaviour will naturally al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the Bitterneſs of Diſſention, and quench the Coals of Schiſm: It will render Charity triumphant over Diviſion; and, if it were poſſible, make us one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, tho of different Minds. A care not to offend, carries ſo many Charms with it, that it tames the wildeſt Beaſts: it gives that ſecurity of Peace and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:200301:3"/>Repoſe, that it perſwades or ſhames the worſt of Tempers into an acquieſcence.</p>
            <p>And here I preſume to lay one Argument before you; which I ſhould think, if diſcretely handled, would very much work upon thoſe, that differ from us. There is a great noiſe made, about the Church enjoyning the Obſervation of things in themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different. And yet I queſtion not, but that the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Oppoſers of this will confeſs, that the ſecular Power may determine the uſe of ſuch things. For otherwiſe there would be an end of all Government, Societies, good Order and Peace in the World: The Conſervation of which conſiſts moſtly in ſuch Laws as are taken up about things indifferent, or ſuch indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Circumſtances of Time, Place, Manner or the like, as would render all ineffectual, if not preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. But if it ſhall be ſaid, This muſt not be done, but where there is ſufficient Reaſon for it: this ſets all to Sea again, and whilſt the infinite Varieties of mans Reaſonings are afloat, no Law can live in ſuch a Storm as they will raiſe. And we do not find, that God has given any other Method for eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the outward Decency and Order of the Church, than what is common to all other Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Men, Civil or Military. Nay the ſtate of the Church is declared to be a Spiritual Warfare. And we know nothing is more rigorous, than Military Diſcipline, even in the minuteſt things.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:200301:4"/>
            <p>We may therefore certainly conclude, that things indifferent in themſelves do not hang ſo looſe to the world: but that for the good of mankind they may be reſtrained from their neutrality. No Body of men in the world can carry on any common purpoſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this power over things indifferent. Should they not deny their Private Liberty, by agreeing to Time and Place, and by tying themſelves up to ſome Rules: it would be like the Confuſion of <hi>Babel,</hi> or like an Army armed at all adventures, where there might poſſibly be found more weapons to offend every one his next man, than to annoy his enemy. So that I do not think I wronged any religious Sect of men in the world: if I ſhould ſay, there is none but what finds it ſelf obliged in ſome meaſure to retrench Private Liberty for the ſake of Common Convenience.</p>
            <p>The true Difference then betwixt the Neceſſity that lies upon things neceſſary in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that which lies upon things indifferent is; that the one is alwaies ſo, and the other only upon occaſion. Which agrees with the juſt and wiſe Declaration of our Church. <hi>The Ceremonies retained are for a Diſcipline and Order, which for a juſt cauſe may be altered and changed: and therefore are not to be eſteemed equal with God's Law.</hi> The caſe being thus, I would gladly know, whether we that obey the Laws made about things indifferent, do not come nearer up to the Precept, <hi>Submit to every ordinance of man for the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:200301:4"/>Lord's ſake,</hi> than they that inſiſt upon an unconfined Liberty.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs by the Principles of ſome, and the Practice of others, one would think there were no Power of God in Rulers, but what were controlable by the will of the Subject: and that Laws were no longer in force, than men had a mind to keep them. But what would be the fate of ſuch a precarious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, our preſent unhappy and ſelf-deſtroying Diviſions give but too broad an intimation. Not but that there are times and ſeaſons to do things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond common allowance. But it is neither conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to preſcribe particulars in ſuch caſes beforehand, nor poſſible to come to an end of them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it has been the wiſdom of all Governments to let alone ſuch Deciſions, till the exigency of affairs call for them. And if at any time ſome upſtart ſcoundrel pretence of a Government has done other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it proved one of the things that moſt expoſed their folly. There may be indeed general Rules, ſuch as our Saviour's for diſpenſing with poſitive Laws, tho of Gods own making, <hi>Man was not made for the ſabbath, but the ſabbath for man,</hi> and that which ſurmounts all, <hi>Neceſſity has no Law:</hi> but the Laws; as I may call them, for ſuch particular occaſions, muſt ariſe out of the exigencies themſelves, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand or fall by the Judgement of Mankind.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:200301:5"/>
            <p n="2">II. The thing we next confidered, was how to prevent the Abuſes, ill men might make of this Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: who, we might eaſily perceive, would be apt to pervert the eaſineſs of the Government, which was intended to favour weak Conſciences, into an occaſion of Profaneſs and Diſorderlineſs. For we find already how much forwarder wicked men are to abuſe this Indulgence, than others to be thankful for it. There are numbers of late, who have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Church, not to go to a Meeting; but either to the Ale-houſe, or to loyter in the fields, or to ſtay at home, and that ſometimes to follow worldly Buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſuppreſs theſe grievous Diſorders, as much as may be; we thought the firſt ſtep to be made, was to call upon the Civil Magiſtrate. For the Laws are many and ſtrict againſt Tipling, Swearing, and the like. So that if the Juſtices would but ſeriouſly and conſcientiouſly ſet themſelves to the execution of them: it could not miſs of having a very good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Eſpecially if they would diſtinguiſh the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane withdrawers from thoſe that are protected by the Act of Toleration, by making them to pay twelve pence a <hi>Sunday</hi> according to the Statute of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Secular Powers are not leſs concerned in their Province to diſcourage Idleneſs and Debauchery upon a Temporal account; than we are to do it upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:200301:5"/>a Religious one. Let them but conſider what mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal wounds ſuch Licentiouſneſs gives to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. It takes off the Strength and Vigour of men; it mightily abates their Care and Induſtry: And that brings them to Want and Neceſſity. And what is the conſequence of all this? They will not be ſo able to follow their own buſineſs in time of Peace, nor ſo ſtout to ſerve their Country in the Wars. Land will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed for want of due Cultivating, and fall in value. Trade will decay. And this will make Taxes more uneaſie every day than other: till Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content with their preſent condition makes the people murmur and fond of any Change, and ſo ripe for Sedition and Rebellion. If then Security be the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Bleſſing to any Nation, when all ſorts of people are content and at their eaſe: what a Curſe is it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be unſafe, and under the continual appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Diſturbance! And therefore certainly it does in the higheſt degree behove the Government to watch againſt ſuch Diſorders, as draw after them ſo pernicious conſequences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing to be done for reforming the Manners of this ſort of people, was reaſonably judged to be the duty incumbent upon our ſelves; out of a Spiritual conſideration to endeavour by all ways to reduce them to a ſober mind, that they might ſeriouſly reflect upon thoſe things that belong to their eternal peace. For if we could once make men good Chriſtians, they would infallibly become
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:200301:6"/>good Subjects, good Neighbours, and whatever elſe might conduce to publick or private convenience. For the effecting of this, we could not think of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſe, nor I believe can we, than to lay that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Kings before us, which is directed to me to be communicated to the two Provinces of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> dated the 13th. day of <hi>February</hi> 1689/1690. I mean that part of it which directs the Preaching againſt ſuch Diſorderlineſs, as is taken notice of in the ſeveral Acts of Parliament againſt Blaſphemy, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Perjury, Drunkenneſs and Prophaning of the Lords day. In the proſecution of which, care ought to be had in the firſt place to time the ſeveral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes to the moſt ſuitable and proper ſeaſons. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. ſays <hi>Demoſthenes, Whoever neglects the right ſeaſon of doing his buſineſs; muſt remember, that the Gods bleſs no ſuch endeavours.</hi> The meaning of which is, That Providence has ſet Rules and Meaſures, and Times and Seaſons for all things: and if we will not be directed by them, we put ourſelves out of the Conduct and Protection of Providence ſo far, as not reaſonably to expect the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of it. And therefore the Prophet boaſts of his wiſdom in this particular, <hi>The Lord God has given me the tongue of the learned, that I ſhould know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon.</hi> Iſa. 50.4.</p>
            <p>So that the firſt thing to be done, is to conſider what may be the propereſt time to Preach upon any of theſe Subjects above mentioned. For however
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:200301:6"/>there may be too much reaſon to make all times ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for ſuch Diſcourſes: yet there are ſome ſeaſons more proper for it perchance than others. As before the <hi>Lent</hi> and <hi>Midſummer</hi> Aſſizes, to make the people underſtand the horrid guilt of the ſin of Perjury, ſo pernicious to particular perſons, ſo deſtructive to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, and ſo highly offenſive to Almighty God. To warn your Flocks in the time of <hi>Advent</hi> againſt the beaſtly ſin of Drunkenneſs, and that which is the conſtant Fruit of it, Blaſpheming and Swearing: that, if poſſible, the ſhameful abuſe of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies may, in ſome meaſure at leaſt, be prevented; when inſtead of ſpiritual Rejoycing and giving of Thanks, nothing but Luxury, Intemperance and the moſt idle Recreations are indulged. And in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to take the time betwixt <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide</hi> for preaching againſt the prophanation of the Lords day: Both becauſe <hi>Eaſter</hi> is the Original of all the reſt of the Lords daies: and becauſe it is in the midſt of thoſe Primitive Holy days <hi>Goodfriday, Eaſter, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion</hi> and <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> whoſe obſervation ſeems to be as early as the time of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>When we are reſolved of the Times: it will be fit to take up a courage ſuitable to the Cauſe we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take. It is Gods Cauſe: we are Advocates for his Truth. And if God be for us, we ought not to ſtand in awe of any man. Frowns and threats, nay and ill uſage to boot, are but Grimaces, in compariſon of his Rewards. And therefore we ought to do our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:200301:7"/>Duty without reſpect of perſons, applying the words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ourſelves, <hi>Theſe things ſpeak and exhort, and rebuke with all authority. Let no man deſpiſe thee.</hi> Tit. 2.15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, We ſhould endeavour to prevail with our diſſenting Brethren, who Teach in Meetings, to joyn heartily with us in diſcouraging looſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons, by keeping them at a diſtance, and expoſing them to the Law. For God knows, it is but too natural for any Society of men to embrace thoſe with all their faults, who will quit another Party to come over to them. But if we could once weather this point: it might be a means to remove many Scandals, which are now given with impunity.</p>
            <p>To be ſure ſuch a friendly compliance would won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully contribute to the reviving that ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed and forgotten vertue among us of Chriſtian Charity. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Treatiſe againſt the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> concerning Baptiſm, obſerves frequently, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Diſcourſe, the great difference there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the behaviour of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> whoſe authority was urged againſt him, and that of the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> and what different effects they had. Particularly <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 18. having taken notice that this Opinion of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his Council of Biſhops was declared before any General Council had determined the Point, whether they that had been Baptized by He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks or Schiſmaticks, ſhould be Baptized again, when they returned into the boſom of the Church:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:200301:7"/>He marks further, that the Peace of the Church was preſerved in the main, becauſe the Communion was not broken. And therefore he willingly cloſes with them in their Appeal to this holy Martyr, thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing himſelf, <hi>Ut ad illum jam veniam, de cujus ſibi authoritate iſti carnaliter blandiuntur, cùm ejus charitate ſpiritualiter perimantur.</hi> He chearfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs with them in comparing his Caſe with theirs, ſince, whilſt they ſo much flattered themſelves after a carnal manner with his Authority, they were ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually confounded by his eminent Charity.</p>
            <p>Now tho we are not ſo happy, as to be able to perſwade thoſe that differ from us to hold Church-Communion with us: Yet a familiar and friendly Converſation would go a great way to prevent thoſe many Miſchiefs and Scandals, which the irreconcila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and extravagant Separation of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> brought upon the Church. It would by degrees diſcover many Miſtakes, and remove many Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices. The Difficulties would not ſeem near ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperable, our Breaches half ſo wide, nor the Points in Controverſie of near that conſequence. Honeſt, plain, well-meaning Hearts would by this means ſoon find out one another, and leave the malicious and perverſe Deſigners naked, and deſtitute of a Cloak for their Knavery. Which might be a means through the help of God's Grace to reclaim even theſe alſo at the laſt, by making them aſhamed of the Evil of their ways, when they find themſelves ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:200301:8"/>laid open. And thus might we hope once, at the laſt, to ſee Truth and Sincerity triumph over Error and Hypocriſie, in this our now unfortunately divided and diſtracted Nation.</p>
            <p n="3">III. In the third place we found it abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to lay carefully the firſt Principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by frequent Catechiſing. For it is certain, the root of all our bitterneſs proceeds from the want of a timely Inſtitution in the true grounds of Piety and Virtue. But eſpecially ought we to preſs the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of <hi>Obedience to Parents and Maſters, with due and modeſt Reſpect and Behaviour towards Superiors.</hi> For the neglect of this firſt Obedience and Submiſſion through want of early Inſtruction, has been the chief Cauſe of all that Refractorineſs and inſolent Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Governours and Magiſtrates. <hi>He that loves not his Brother, whom he has ſeen: how can he love God,</hi> ſays S. <hi>John, whom he has not ſeen?</hi> So it is in the point of Obedience and Submiſſion; he that obeys not his Parents, whom he ſees daily, how ſhall he obey his Prince whom he neither has, nor it may be ever will ſee? Therefore God's Law appointed, that a ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Son ſhould be put to death, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. thereby to let us underſtand, that a diſobedient Son would never make a good Subject. For when he is once grown beadſtrong, he makes no diſtinction, let who will hold the Reins. If he will not obey his Parents or Maſter, it is becauſe he is proud, obſtinate, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will'd:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:200301:8"/>and what is a Magiſtrate to expect from ſuch a Temper? I wiſh I could ſay, that all this empty noiſe, that we make about Religion and Liberty, were not the Blind to this unhappy Diſpoſition, which has ſo overſpread the Nation with Malice and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            <p>We ought therefore earneſtly to ſet our Hearts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. And if we will pull up Diſſention by the root, we muſt poſſeſs the Hearts of the People with a juſt ſenſe of their Duty, at leaſt in that part of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which teaches Submiſſion and ſtudying to be quiet. Let it be the Subject of our Sermons and the Entertainment of our Diſcourſe, as well as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our Catechiſm. Let no opportunity eſcape the Improvement of this Duty, without which the <hi>Watchman waketh but in vain.</hi> In ſhort, <hi>Hinc illae lachrymae;</hi> and till this bleating of Rebellion be ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie'd upon the Altar of Obedience, we muſt expect no Peace in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But if this Virtue once prevail, it will carry along with it that godly Awe and Fear, as cannot fail to work a Reformation of Manners. And for this reaſon the Pſalmiſt makes it the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Repentance, <hi>Stand in awe and ſin not;</hi> and the original of that Wiſdom which is from above, <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom.</hi> For it is a Quality that ſo ſeaſons the Heart, that it bleſſes the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all other Chriſtian Virtues. <hi>God gives grace to the humble,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> v.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:200301:9"/>
            <p>But after all, our Inſtructions will be very lame, without the Concurrence of Parents and Maſters of Families. Tho we urge never ſo powerfully, be our Reaſons never ſo ſtrong, and tho we ſhould ſpeak with the Tongue of Men and Angels, without ſomething of the Bit and Bridle, we ſhall do but little good. The generality of Youth are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of reaſoning, and they that are, through the giddineſs and folly of their childiſh Age, cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it. Alas! We ſee in thoſe of riper Years, to whom the Excellence of Reaſon makes a fair ſhew, whilſt it is exerciſed in the Theory; if you come to attacque their Luſts, by preſſing the Rule home to their Practice, it is immediately repulſed with Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and overwhelmed oftentimes with a torrent of corrupt Affections. The Vapors of Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence fly up and turn the Brains and dim the Sight, that Men can neither underſtand what is for their real good, nor ſee the Miſchief into which they are running. The generality of Men have nothing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent left them for their preſervation, but that which is common to them with Beaſts, fear of preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and that hardly breaks through the incumbrance of ſome Paſſions. For this cauſe it is, that the Awe of Parents and Maſters muſt firſt make an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and break the ſturdineſs of Nature at the firſt entrance upon the days of Youth; if we will expect to do any good afterwards. <hi>With-hold not correction from the child, for if thou beatest him with the rod, he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:200301:9"/>ſhall not die. Thou ſhalt beat him with the rod, and ſhalt deliver his ſoul from hell.</hi> Prov. 23.13, 14. The Frown of a Parent ſpeaks preſent Inconvenience; the young Man's preſent Maintenance is at his Will, as well as his future Hopes. The Diſpleaſure of a Maſter threatens immediate Miſchief; he may turn out of Doors, and make it difficult to get Bread. Theſe are the means to bow the ſtiff Neck, and make the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractorineſs of Youth comply with Inſtruction. For this cauſe then ought the Duty of Parents and Maſters to their Families to be as home preſſed, as the Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal: And the rather, for that it is generally forgot in this Age. It is not conſidered, as it ſhould be, what a Charge lies upon thoſe, that have Families: The Blood of the meaneſt of which, if they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry by the ill Example or Neglect of the other, will be required at their hands.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. In the laſt place we can have no reaſon to expect a Bleſſing upon our Endeavours, unleſs they be done with Sincerity. We muſt not only preach to others the Word of Life; but ſo behave our ſelves, as they that would partake with them in the ſame Bleſſedneſs: That by ſeeing our good Works, they may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven. God indeed may proſper good Inſtructions to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of others; tho they that delivered them, ſhould prove Reprobates: But there is no Thanks due to ſuch a Perſon, who takes the readieſt way to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw his good Doctrine by his ill Example.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:200301:10"/>
            <p>It may be imagined, that Hypocriſie might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the defect of a ſincere Mind in promoting God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. But when the Nature and Deſigns of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie are well conſidered, and Experience examined upon it, we ſhall ſoon be convinced to the contrary. For no Hypocriſie can be laid on ſo thick, but that the Stains of Vice will in a little time work through it ſo, that every ſincere Eye may perceive it. And therefore we find by ſad Experience, that they who lie long under the direction of Hypocriſie, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Hypocrites themſelves, or through Weakneſs are deluded into the Doctrines of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly profeſs that Evil, which Hypocrites have repreſented to them for good.</p>
            <p>After all, It will not ſuffice that we avoid giving Scandal in our Lives and Converſation, or forbear the endeavouring to cover it with Hypocriſie: unleſs we deteſt doing the work of the Lord negligently. God has declared, that he will ſpew out thoſe that are lukewarm. If we will be Labourers worthy our hire, we muſt put on a Spirit ſuitable to the <hi>High Calling</hi> we are employed about. We have not only to conſider the object, which is no leſs than Eternal Happineſs, but the part we have in the purſuit of it. We are to be Lights to others, as well as to our ſelves. A double diligence is required at our hands; as having taken upon us to watch for others, as well as for our ſelves. Which will by no means conſiſt with a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine or indifferent behaviour either thro lazineſs of temper, or too much addiction to the world. All
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:200301:10"/>works go on, juſt as they are proſecuted. Where people are intent and vigilant, their undertakings go on proſperouſly: but where they are remiſs and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, nothing ſucceeds. There are ſome Attempts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that may be fruſtrated by reaſon of inſuperable difficulties, or given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er as not worth the toyl and labour: but neither of theſe Diſcouragements can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take place in our caſe. For the reward is more than ſufficient to countervail all that we can undergo, <hi>I count all things but loſs for the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord.</hi> Phil. 3.8. and we muſt never pretend that any Difficulties can be too great for us, when the Holy Ghoſt has taught every one of us to ſay, <hi>I can do all things thro Chriſt which ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth me.</hi> Phil. 4.13. I am perſuaded you cannot but have reflected upon theſe things over and over: ſince we have almoſt freſh inſtances dayly to ſtir up our minds and awaken us to our Duty. But the Fleſh is weak, and will incline us to avoid all hardſhips, if we will hearken to it. Continual oppoſition and contradiction is uneaſie to fleſh and blood: and when it comes from thoſe we ſeek and take pains to inform better, it muſt needs be very grievous. But this can be no ſurprize to thoſe that have heard the words of him that has undergone the contradiction of ſinners for us, <hi>In the world ye ſhall have tribulation.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the words of St. <hi>Peter, Think it not ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fiery trial which is to try you, as tho ſome ſtrange thing happened unto you: but rejoyce, in as much as ye are partakers of Christs ſufferings; that when his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:200301:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>glory ſhall be revealed, ye may be glad alſo with exceeding joy.</hi> And <hi>The God of all grace who has called us unto his eternal glory by Chriſt Jeſus, after that ye have ſuffered a while, make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you.</hi> Which is the daily Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 29. 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt Affectionate Friend and Brother, H. <hi>London.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:200301:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
